If you look deep into the night sky,
إذا نظرت بتمعن إلى السماء ليلا،
you see stars,
سترى النجوم،
and if you look further, you see more stars,
وإذا نظرت بتمعن أكثر، سترى نجوما أكثر،
and further, galaxies, and further, more galaxies.
أبعد من ذلك سترى المجرات، وأبعد أكثر، مجرات أكثر،
But if you keep looking further and further,
ولكن إن واصلت النظر بعمق أكثر فأكثر،
eventually you see nothing for a long while,
ففي النهاية سترى فراغا لمدة طويلة،
and then finally you see a faint, fading afterglow,
وفي الأخير سترى ضوء خافتا، وشفقا يتلاشى،
and it's the afterglow of the Big Bang.
وهذا شفق الانفجار العظيم.
Now, the Big Bang was an era in the early universe
الآن الانفجار العظيم، كان عصرا في الكون الأولي،
when everything we see in the night sky
حين كان كل ما نراه الآن في السماء ليلا،
was condensed into an incredibly small,
مكثفا في كتلة صغيرة بشكل مدهش،
incredibly hot, incredibly roiling mass,
شديدة الحرارة، ومكدرة جدا،
and from it sprung everything we see.
ومنها انبثق كل شيء نراه.
Now, we've mapped that afterglow
لقد رسمنا هذا الشفق
with great precision,
بشكل دقيق جدا،
and when I say we, I mean people who aren't me.
وعندما أتكلم بصيغة الجمع، أعني أشخاصا غيري.
We've mapped the afterglow
لقد رسمنا خريطة هذا الشفق،
with spectacular precision,
بدقة متناهية،
and one of the shocks about it
وأحد الحقائق الصادمة حولها،
is that it's almost completely uniform.
هي أنها في متماثلة بشكل كبير جدا.
Fourteen billion light years that way
14 مليار سنة ضوئية في هذا الاتجاه
and 14 billion light years that way,
و14 مليار سنة ضوئية في هذا الاتجاه،
it's the same temperature.
بنفس الحرارة.
Now it's been 14 billion years
مرت الآن 14 مليار سنة
since that Big Bang,
على الانفجار العظيم،
and so it's got faint and cold.
وقد يبدو الآن باهتا وباردا.
It's now 2.7 degrees.
درجة حرارته الآن هي 2.7.
But it's not exactly 2.7 degrees.
لكن ليست 2.7 بالضبط.
It's only 2.7 degrees to about
هي 2.7 درجة من أصل
10 parts in a million.
10 أجزاء من المليون.
Over here, it's a little hotter,
لدينا هنا، فالأمر أكثر حرارة بعض الشيء،
and over there, it's a little cooler,
لكن هناك، فهو أكثر برودة إلى حد ما،
and that's incredibly important to everyone in this room,
وهذا مهم للغاية بالنسبة لكل الحاضرين في هذه القاعة،
because where it was a little hotter,
لأنه في المكان الذي كان أكثر حرارة شيئا ما،
there was a little more stuff,
كانت تحدث أمور أكثر،
and where there was a little more stuff,
وحيث كانت تحدث أمور أكثر،
we have galaxies and clusters of galaxies
وُجِدت لدينا مجرات ومجموعات مجرية
and superclusters
فمجموعات أكبر،
and all the structure you see in the cosmos.
وكل النظام الذي ترونه في الكون.
And those small, little, inhomogeneities,
وتلك الأجزء الصغيرة والقليلة والمتجانسة،
20 parts in a million,
تلكم العشرون جزء من المليون،
those were formed by quantum mechanical wiggles
تكونت عن طريق ذبذبات ميكانيكيا الكم
in that early universe that were stretched
في عصر الكون الأولي الذي تمدد
across the size of the entire cosmos.
على مدى حجم الكون كله.
That is spectacular,
هذا مذهل،
and that's not what they found on Monday;
لكن ليس هذا ما تم اكتشافه يوم الإثنين؛
what they found on Monday is cooler.
ما اكتشفوه يوم الإثنين كان أكثر روعة.
So here's what they found on Monday:
إليكم ما اكتشفوه يوم الإثنين:
Imagine you take a bell,
تخيل أن لديك جرسا،
and you whack the bell with a hammer.
وبدأت تضرب الجرس بمطرقة.
What happens? It rings.
مالذي سيحدث؟ سيرن الجرس.
But if you wait, that ringing fades
لكن إن انتظرت، فسيتلاشى ذلك الرنين
and fades and fades
شيئا فشيئا
until you don't notice it anymore.
حتى تتوقف عن سماعه نهائيا.
Now, that early universe was incredibly dense,
الآن ، ذلك الكون الأولي كان كثيفا بشكل كبير،
like a metal, way denser,
مثل المعدن، وأكثر كثافة بكثير،
and if you hit it, it would ring,
حيث إنك حين تضربه، فسيحدث رنينا،
but the thing ringing would be
لكن الشيء الذي سيرن سيكون
the structure of space-time itself,
نظام الزمكان نفسه،
and the hammer would be quantum mechanics.
والمطرقة ستكون ميكانيكا الكم.
What they found on Monday
ما وجدوه يوم الإثنين
was evidence of the ringing
كان دليلا عن رنين
of the space-time of the early universe,
نظام الزمكان المتعلق بالكون الأولي،
what we call gravitational waves
ما نسميه موجات الجاذبية
from the fundamental era,
من العصر الأساسي،
and here's how they found it.
وإليكم كيف اكتشفوا ذلك.
Those waves have long since faded.
مر زمن طويل على تلاشي تلك الموجات.
If you go for a walk,
إذا خرجت لتتمشى،
you don't wiggle.
فإنك لا تتأرجح.
Those gravitational waves in the structure of space
موجات الجاذبية تلك الموجودة في بنية الفضاء
are totally invisible for all practical purposes.
غير مرئية تماما لأسباب عملية.
But early on, when the universe was making
لكن قبل هذا، حين كان الكون يُحدِث
that last afterglow,
آخر شفق،
the gravitational waves
كانت موجات الجاذبية
put little twists in the structure
تضع تلك اللمسات الصغيرة على تركيبة
of the light that we see.
الضوء الذي نراه.
So by looking at the night sky deeper and deeper --
وبالتالي، ومن خلال النظر إلى السماء ليلا بشكل أعمق فأعمق -
in fact, these guys spent three years on the South Pole
ففي الواقع، أمضى هؤلاء الناس 3 سنوات في القطب الجنوبي
looking straight up through the coldest, clearest,
ينظرون نحو الأعلى من خلال الهواء الأبرد والأوضح
cleanest air they possibly could find
والأنقى الذي تمكنوا من إيجاده
looking deep into the night sky and studying
ينظرون بتمعن إلى السماء ليلا، ويدرسون
that glow and looking for the faint twists
ذلك التوهج، ويبحثون عن تلك الخيوط المتلاشية
which are the symbol, the signal,
التي تعتبر رمز وإشارة،
of gravitational waves,
موجات الجاذبية،
the ringing of the early universe.
رنين الكون الأولي.
And on Monday, they announced
وفي يوم الاثنين أعلنوا
that they had found it.
أنهم اكتشفوه.
And the thing that's so spectacular about that to me
والأمر المدهش هنا بالنسبة لي
is not just the ringing, though that is awesome.
ليس الرنين، رغم أنه مذهل.
The thing that's totally amazing,
لكن الأمر المدهش للغاية،
the reason I'm on this stage, is because
والذي هو سبب تواجدي على هذا المسرح،
what that tells us is something deep about the early universe.
أن هذا يخبرنا عن شيء عميق متعلق بالكون
It tells us that we
يخبرنا بأننا
and everything we see around us
نحن وجميع الأشياء من حولنا
are basically one large bubble --
أننا بالأساس داخل فقاعة ضخمة -
and this is the idea of inflation—
وهذه هي فكرة التضخم الكوني -
one large bubble surrounded by something else.
فقاعة ضخمة محاطة بشيء آخر.
This isn't conclusive evidence for inflation,
وهذا ليس دليلا قاطعا على تضخم الكون،
but anything that isn't inflation that explains this
لكن أي شيء آخر يفسر هذا غير التضخم
will look the same.
سوف يبدو مماثلا.
This is a theory, an idea,
هذه نظرية، فكرة،
that has been around for a while,
كانت تدور منذ بعض الوقت،
and we never thought we we'd really see it.
لكننا لم نكن نتوقع أننا سنراها.
For good reasons, we thought we'd never see
لعدة أسباب معتبرة، لم نكن نتوقع أننا سنرى
killer evidence, and this is killer evidence.
دليلا قاطعا عنها، وهذا دليل قاطع.
But the really crazy idea
لكن الفكرة الجنونية فعلا هنا
is that our bubble is just one bubble
هي أن فقاعتنا، هي فقاعة
in a much larger, roiling pot of universal stuff.
داخل إناء عكر وعريض جدا مليء بالأشياء الكونية.
We're never going to see the stuff outside,
لايمكننا أبدا أن نرى هذه الأشياء في الخارج،
but by going to the South Pole and spending three years
لكن من خلال الذهاب إلى القطب الجنوبي وقضاء 3 سنوات هناك،
looking at the detailed structure of the night sky,
والنظر إلى تفاصيل بنية السماء ليلا،
we can figure out
يمكننا أن نعرف
that we're probably in a universe that looks kind of like that.
أننا ربما نعيش في كون يشبه هذا.
And that amazes me.
وهذا أمر يدهشني.
Thanks a lot.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)